Hey, hey, and welcome back to living in
central Texas. If you are considering
relocating to the area, whether that's
Temple, Belton, Celo, Colleen, or any of
the surrounding areas, there are some
major shifts in our housing market that
you need to know about. Prices are up in
some areas, they're down in a lot of
others, and inventory is changing fast.
We are no longer in the same competitive
chaos we were over the last couple of
years. Hi, I'm Andrea Dudik, realtor and
associate broker, and I help buyers,
sellers, and relocating families
navigate Central Texas real estate with
confidence and clarity. In today's
video, I'm breaking down the May 2025
housing stats and comparing them to last
year and even looking at what's just
changed over the last 5 years. Let's get
started.
[Music]
Let's go ahead and look at the state of
Texas.
So, here you can see we have Texas,
right? And what we're going to focus on
today is Bell County. Bell County is
highlighted here in red.
And if we zoom in, we have Temple,
Belton,
Celo,
and Colleen. Those are the statistics
that we'll be covering today.
And then I also serve really everything
just in and just outside of these areas.
If you like more information on
navigating the area or kind of learning
where everything is, you can head on
over to the website livinginctx.com.
And on the homepage, we have this really
awesome interactive map that you can
click around, play with where everything
is, and it'll give you information on
the area, houses in the area,
statistics.
I'll just show you one. You click on
Belton. So, it's got market reports,
schools, featured listings, and then I
have videos that are in alignment with
that area, some YouTube videos. Okay?
So, really cool resource if you want to
head on over and check that out. But for
today's video, we're going to be looking
at market statistics of Bell County and
those particularly particular areas I
discussed, Temple, Belton, Celo, and
Colleen. So over the last 5 years,
Central Texas has exploded in growth.
Vel County especially has become a
magnet for people that are looking for
affordability,
more space, and a slower pace. Um,
without losing access to Austin, Waco or
Fort Hood. We I think changed names to
Fort Bazos, and then now it looks like
we're back to Fort Hood. So, if you can
see on this map,
you have Waco up here, Austin down here.
Some of those um very popular towns
right now also being Georgetown, Round
Rock, of course, remember anytime that
you go towards Austin, your house prices
are going to go up compared to where we
are. And then again, as you go to Waco,
your home prices are going to go up as
well. So, Waco, Austin, and then Fort
Cavazos is like right out here.
Temple and Belton have grown steadily
thanks to major employers like Baylor,
Scott and White, Mlan, Texas&M,
um, Central Texas nearby. Colleen is a
major key market for military families,
while Celo has carved out its space as a
high-end lifestyle driven town. I've
heard that it's kind of the new
Fredericksburg of our area. It's um kind
of fancy and you know, golf golf course
living, you know, uh Mil Creek golf
course out there. you have a lot of
upand cominging communities like brand
new communities while again of course
still some of the more beautiful
established communities and uh you're
not you're not 15 20 minutes away from
Temple and all of Temple's amenities
does I did just do a video on Sato if
you want to check that out but it does
have its own grocery store and um not
being far from all of our temple grocery
store shopping dining etc but now in
2025 we're starting to see the after
effects of high interest rates, new
construction inventory, and buyer
fatigue. So, what do those numbers
actually tell us? Well,
if you would like to follow along with
today's statistics, you can go to
myt.com, mtb.com.
Scroll on down to where we see market
statistics for your housing area. Click
here to view. I found that these links
here aren't working on my computer. Um,
so they might be down, but here are the
housing reports for Bell County. My
tabboard.com is the Central Texas um
Temple Belton Board of Realtors.
So, we're going to start with Temple.
Median price 279,
down 3.3%
from May of 2024.
Active listings are up 33.3%
since May of last year,
which means we have a lot of homes on
the market, a lot more homes on the
market. Days on market, so 80 days on
market, that's before a home gets an
offer and goes under contract. And then
days to close is 28. So 80 days hanging
out until we get that bite, get under
contract. Another 28 days to close. It's
about 108 days than the previous year,
which is slightly less than last year,
which I think is interesting. Closed
sales are up 13%.
Temple is starting to level out, so
prices dipped slightly. Inventory
jumped, meaning there are more options
and more breathing room for buyers. We
are in a hardcore buyers market at the
moment. Um, and nearly 40% of all
listings are priced between 200 and
300,000. So, if you're relocating from a
higher cost of living area, your dollar
stretches further here. And for sellers,
it means you need to price smart and be
ready to stand out because buyers have
choices now. And not only do they have
choices between your home, but also
between new construction. And those
builders are throwing incentives at
them. Um, so Belton, we're going to hop
on over to Belton. Median price in
Belton of 340138.
So slightly higher median price. 31.5%
from May of last year. Inventory is at
5.7 months. So what does inventory mean?
Inventory means that if there was there
were no new homes coming on the market,
how long would it take for us to sell
out of inventory with the current rate
of that homes are selling at? So, um,
last year we were at 5.6. This we're at
about 5.7. That kind of surprised me.
Active listings are up 36.8%.
So, still a ton more inventory than we
had last year. dominant price range
again being between 300 and 400,000.
Belton has seen one of the most dramatic
jumps in both price and demand. Um why?
And that that's because um its location,
school, and charms. Belt nicity is one
of the most sought after school
districts in our area. Uh the his we
have historic the historic town lake
access. I love Lake Belton. There's also
Morgan's Point, which is
um part of Belton ISD. It's a little
just slightly out. Go check out the map,
but I have a video on Morgan's Point as
well if you'd like to check out there.
But lake access, proximity to both
Temple, Fort Hood, just makes it really
attractive for families as well as
professionals alike. Um just you're kind
of near everything that's in this area.
Over 42% of homes fall in that $300 to
$400,000 range, which is right in that
sweet spot for many relocating buyers.
Let's go to So
Housing Report. Median price of 800,000.
This is wrong. I mean,
I really think this is wrong. I can't I
I'm not positive, but I'm I'm pretty So
I would say homes in Cedo are median
would probably be closer to 500,000.
This report also says that there were
only four homes sold in May. That is
wrong. I just went and pulled statistics
from um the MLS and there were over 40
homes closed in the last 30 days. So, I
think this one's a little something
someone mistyped here, but um we're
still going to talk about. So,
median house prices I I went and looked.
So, there were about oh, there were 32
sales in the last 30 days. Um ranging
from 250,000 to 955,000
and over 34 of those homes were above
400,000. So it is still the median house
price in is still higher than Temple
Belton and Colleen by far. Um and again
it just has kind of that more upscale uh
vibe and more luxury feel um with the
golf golf course living and uh very it's
got like a winery. Uh lots of time spent
downtown Celo Creek. It's just Salo is
its own vibe. It's really cool. If you
want to see it, go check out the video I
did on Celo, Texas. It's a boutique
market, so a lot of homes here are on
larger lots. Um, if you're looking for
that peace, privacy, and upscale charm.
Days on market are shorter here. Uh, but
it it is this is not a volume market per
se. If you're relocating and looking
looking for something truly special and
quiet, so is definitely worth a tour,
and I'd love to give it to you. I'm
going to pop on over to Colleen.
This is a hot spot for many people
coming to the area because of Fort Hood.
We are um a huge area for especially
first-time buyers and military families
using their VA loans. Um Colleen is one
of the most affordable mark markets in
central Texas.
Median price is in that 225
950 range.
It's down a little bit from May of last
year. Active listings are up 24%. So, we
can see across all of these that they're
the inventory is increasing. Again,
telling us that it's more of a buyer
market. Inventory is at 4.9 months
compared and up from 3.4 last year. And
closed sales are down 20%. There's just
a lot of inventory and a lot less people
buying. Definitely these interest rates
are scaring people, but mind you, there
are so many builders and sellers w
willing to offer incentives to help buy
down that rate. So, it's really, really
great opportunity to get a great deal on
a home if you can afford it. Um, my
whole thing is time your availability to
purchase and not necessarily the market
cuz we have no idea what these interest
rates are going to do. But if you can
pay into your own mortgage, I do
recommend it. Um, so Colleen is one of
the most affordable markets in central
Texas. Let's see. Over half the homes
fall between 200,000 and 299,000.
And you can still find homes under 250
here, which is a super rarity these
days. While closed sales are down and
days on market is up, buyers here have
more time and less pressure to decide
and make a purchase.
For investors, this could be a really
great entry point. So, what does this
all mean? Um, across the board, we're
moving into what feels like a more
balanced market. Buyers have more
inventory and more leverage than they've
had in the past few years and the past 3
years. Sellers can still win, but
pricing and presentation are more
important than ever. Um, you know, if
we're selling your home, we really want
to make sure that we're strategic in how
we're pricing, but of because of course
there is what your home is worth in a
value perspective and what the market is
willing to pay for it. And right now,
buyers aren't willing to pay top dollar
because they have so many houses to to
pick from. So our best bet is to price
your home appropriately so that we are
not price dropping and extending those
days on market which encourages lower
offers and presentation
you you know don't want to take photos
from your iPhone. We you know the
presentation with strong photographer
videography I do things like put you on
YouTube and then um staging. Staging
really matters. So presenting your home
in a very special and beautiful way
definitely matters now more than ever.
Temple is great for affordab
affordability with access to hospitals
and schools. I harp in this all the
time, but we are the largest medical hub
between Austin and Dallas. We're a huge
teaching facility. Um we see lots of
traveling nurses, res residents. We have
the VA hospital here. Belton is gaining
traction for charming, familyfriendly
with fast closing. We know is high-end,
low density, and Colleen still offers
the best entrylevel affordability, but
they all have very different feels. So,
I recommend that you take a look around,
explore the areas. You're going to find
what kind of falls into all of your
wants and needs. If you're relocating,
this is a f If you're relocating, this
is a fantastic time to explore options
and make thoughtful moves, not rushed
decisions. I hope this gave you a
clearer picture of the central Texas
market. If you're considering
relocating, whether it's this summer or
6 months from now, I'd love to help you
find the right fit. Make sure to head on
over to livingx.com
where again we have that really awesome
interactive map where you can explore
every suburb, um, watch neighborhood
tours videos, and even fill out a short
form to book a one- on-one planning call
with me. And don't forget to like this
video, subscribe to the channel, and
drop any questions you have below in the
comments. I'm here to make your move
smooth, smart, and stressfree. Till next
time.
[Music]